You lose more money holding other altcoins or shitcoins or trying to follow the trends.
Life-changing type of wealth creation.
I think that this is something that will be huge in the future because it's very easy for the mainstream investor to understand it.
But you have to jump when it's started.
Hello, it's Bonnie. In this episode, we'll be talking to one of the most interesting people I've ever met in crypto.
He's from Spain. He gave out a lot of bitcoins on the street to random people when it was dirt cheap.
So that's how long he's been in crypto.
He's worked at Binance, FTX, and now at CoinCall, a platform that focuses on crypto options trading.
You might be wondering why.
Maybe because Bloomberg says options trading is the hottest thing right now on Wall Street.
Since he has seen all the bear and bull markets, I'm going to ask him to predict the next bull run.
Let's welcome Cheviar.
Hi.
Let's talk about how long you've been in crypto and what's the journey like?
Well, I was lucky to start early, actually, because I was still at the university.
It was in 2012 when I first knew about Bitcoin.
And I was reading articles about finance because I graduated in economics.
So I came across an article that was talking about a euro for Africa.
So the same that we have in Europe, but for Africa.
And they were talking about a digital currency that was going to be used among the population there using their mobile phones because almost no one had a bank account.
And I was very interested about this.
And this coin was called Bitcoin.
After I graduated a few years later, I started working or writing for Cointelegraph, first in Spanish and then in English.
I had a blog about economics.
So a few years later, I also joined Binance in 2019.
I was one of the early employees, one of the first 300.
Now I believe they have more than 8,000 people.
It's huge.
It's a different company, I would say.
But back then, it was more like a startup.
And I was at Binance until 2022 when I decided to join FTX.
I left Binance because I spent there three years.
I thought it was the right time to move on.
During my last weeks, I got an offer from a former colleague from Binance that was working at FTX.
And they told me that they were opening the market in Europe, that they were looking for people.
So I decided to jump.
Back then, it was a good decision, I must say.
I don't regret it.
Nobody could know what was going to happen.
But I enjoyed the short trip at FTX.
After that, like everyone, I also lost money.
My family lost money.
So I decided to go on my own.
Like more or less one month later, after the FTX crash, I got a message from a colleague.
And he told me that there was a company called CoinCall that was very interesting,
that I should talk to the CEO and have a call.
So I had a call with the CEO.
He convinced me because there's something that FTX missed.
It was the custody of users' funds.
CoinCall doesn't have the custody of users' funds.
And that was very important for me after what happened.
At least here, we cannot repeat what happened at FTX.
We don't need to do any proof of reserve because we don't have the custody.
And what CoinCall uses is a company, external company called Kobo,
that is specialized in the custody of users' funds.
It has insurance.
So it's much better.
And I felt more confident.
What's the difference between these three exchanges?
Because I feel like they're so different.
Binance, as I was there for three years, the first early stage when I joined,
it was a pure startup.
Binance didn't have anything like only spot, no margin, no futures, nothing.
They started growing really fast in 2020 during the COVID.
You could realize that it was starting to be a different company, more corporate.
That's why I thought it was time to move to a different place or to have a break.
And what I found at FTX was the early Binance.
Even though FTX was huge, was the second biggest exchange and was growing really fast,
they were only 400 employees.
Binance was more or less 8,000.
So only 400 people were doing more or less the job of 8,000 people at Binance.
So it was very surprising to me.
And CoinCall, it's even more a startup because CoinCall is just starting.
So I had the opportunity to live what I couldn't live at FTX or Binance,
which was the beginning of the project, the pure beginning before the launch,
the plan of the strategy, everything.
CoinCall was a very small company when I joined.
They were only, I think, 20 people.
I was probably the second hire or third hire in the marketing team.
Wow.
I see a pattern here.
So you love the startup environment.
Yes.
I love the beginnings.
I love, because it's the moment where you can be more creative.
You can do more things.
You have more growth possibilities for your personal career.
And the most important one is that you learn a lot.
You learn a lot because you have to do everything.
Talking about doing everything, you're also a very OG YouTuber.
Crypto YouTuber.
I was just looking at your channel and you posted your first crypto content like six years ago?
Or seven?
Seven in 2016.
Yeah.
How has that been?
When I started learning about crypto, all the content was mainly in English.
I previously had a blog about finance where I wrote about Bitcoin and I decided to move
from the writing part to the video content part.
So that's why I created the video channel.
Are you planning on continuing this journey?
I'm planning to do so.
Now I have time.
I had to stop the channel when I joined Binance because of conflict of interest.
I want to do more about entertainment.
In 2016, I decided to hide Bitcoins in Barcelona, in the streets of Barcelona.
How did you do that?
Yeah.
I knew you were going to ask this.
So I created paper wallets.
It was a way to store crypto, mainly Bitcoin.
Most of the time, one use wallet.
So I created these paper wallets.
I sent some Bitcoins.
We're talking about a decent amount of money right now because I think back then was 0.2
Bitcoins for some wallets.
So it's a lot of money.
And I printed the paper wallets and I hide them in the streets of Barcelona, like under
a bench or on a light or, I don't know, in different places.
It's on YouTube.
And even Cointelegraph wrote an article about this.
And I thought it was a very fun experience to know about Bitcoin, to have your first Bitcoins.
So you gave out a lot of Bitcoins.
That's what I hear.
I lost a lot on my way, on my journey.
Hey, you had fun.
So you're more like a preacher.
You teach people and you educate.
What is your main goal being in crypto?
Because I assume you're in crypto long enough to just retire and sit on the beach all day.
But you're still here educating.
So what is pushing you?
So unfortunately, I did a lot of mistakes during my years.
This is something very common when you hear someone telling you that I bought Bitcoin in
2012, Ethereum in 2016, things like this.
People think that you are a super millionaire, but they forget that you also sold or you gave
away, like I did, Bitcoins to people.
So why I'm into crypto?
I wouldn't lie if I wouldn't say to make money.
So I think to make money is one of the reasons, but also because it's my hobby.
I like it.
I like what crypto means.
I like the philosophy of this ecosystem.
I like what Bitcoin represents for the freedom of the people.
I'm very scared about CODCs and all this stuff.
Holding Bitcoin and other crypto might be a solution or kind of an escape for some of us
in the future.
I have dreams, expensive dreams sometimes, and I think crypto is going to pay for them.
What's one of them?
Both.
Go to the States, for example.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, that is very expensive.
So let's say you meet someone in their early 30s, normal paying job, and they come across
cryptocurrency for the very first time.
What do you suggest them to do the first two months?
To learn all they can, to learn, to learn, and to learn.
And if they want, they can try with small amounts because at the end, if you practice,
you learn faster.
And it's very easy.
But everything is free on the internet.
All the content is free.
So you don't need to pay any expensive course or something like this.
On YouTube, you have all the content.
Today is 2023.
It's not 2015 or 2016.
You have a lot of content about cryptocurrencies.
So go there and go online and check.
You've worked at Binance FTX CoinCall.
And CoinCall is different because it's focusing on options and futures, right?
Yes.
These are very complicated financial tools.
Can you explain to us in very simple terms, what are the differences between these two?
The main difference between futures and options trading is that futures are a contract that
obligates, that's very important, the buyer to purchase or sell an asset at a specified
date, okay, and price.
While options give the buyer the right, but not the obligation to purchase or sell this asset
at a specified price and time.
So basically with futures, you have the obligation.
With options, you don't have the obligation.
You have the right to buy something in the future.
If we talk about personality, how would you describe the different personality between
like an option trader and a futures trader?
I would say futures is a short-term trader, maybe.
For options, I would say that is more long-term.
Options are less risky than futures.
So probably someone who's less risk averse will prefer options.
So almost all crypto exchanges offer perpetual contracts, right?
So a lot of people in crypto, they're more used to this tool.
But why aren't more exchanges offering options trading?
I think it was a trend.
So before Binance made futures mainstream, because I think it was Binance in 2020, futures were
already available on BitMEX, for example.
Yeah, it's just a matter of the timing.
If back then Binance decided to start with options rather than futures, we'd be talking
right now that futures is the next thing and everything.
So you don't think options are harder?
I think that maybe you have more things to learn in options.
If you already know futures, options shouldn't be very difficult.
If you're starting from zero, it's new content from you.
So it's the same if you learn options and if you learn futures.
I come across this Bloomberg report that says options are the next big thing or is already
the next big thing on Wall Street.
Why is that?
What's your take on this?
In crypto, options trading is very small, still very small.
In the future, this trend will change.
And options will be a huge percentage of the crypto trading volume.
So that's why I wanted to jump in early.
When people start realizing that options are less risky and are not that difficult, they
will prefer options than futures.
Is that your personal preference as well?
Right now, yes.
I mean, before CoinCall, I was only trading futures.
But since I joined CoinCall, I started learning about options because I have to say that I didn't
know about options before.
I mean, I knew what options were, but I didn't trade options.
This vision that CoinCall has convinced me and also the data on traditional finance, it's
a clear proof.
Options is a huge part of the market.
Because I have a few friends that are option traders and honestly, they work an hour a day.
And I'm like, how do you even do that?
I'm so jealous.
Right.
That's another thing.
You don't need to pay attention all the time to be liquidated for market moves or things
like this because you have an expiration date in your options contract.
And until that date, you can decide if you do the purchase or not of this option.
Let's talk about futures first.
What are the data and stats you will look out for before you start a trade?
Well, I would say first what cryptocurrency I want to trade.
I will check also any related news.
You always have to pay attention on the news, analyze the chart, check the trends, check also
the liquidations.
How are they positioned it?
And many things.
It depends on each crypto.
So what's your approach on setting stop losses?
Why is it so hard for people to admit that they're wrong?
Well, I think you answered the question.
So how greedy are you if you know when it's enough?
Everyone should fix a target for the profits that they want to take.
It's a matter of managing your risk very well.
How do you decide when to take profit personally?
I don't do more than 10%.
I think 5% to 10%.
In my personal opinion, it's quite safe sometimes.
I think that is right.
Like manage your risk.
And, you know, everyone has different risk tolerance and people should just understand that.
Now we can talk about options.
So if a newbie comes to you and be like, I want to learn options.
Where should I start?
What would you suggest?
Of course, I will suggest to join CoinCall because something that we have and other platforms
that offer options don't have is personalized masterclasses and tutors.
You can join our Telegram chat.
Have a conversation with us.
You can chat with the tutor.
You can ask him whatever you want.
And we do weekly masterclasses.
Again, open to everyone.
And you can join.
And you can learn.
And you can ask whatever you want.
And then you can decide to join CoinCall and test what you have learned or to practice.
So I would recommend everyone that wants to learn about options to join us.
We also offer altcoin options.
And this is not something that other platforms do.
Usually all the other platforms, they have only Bitcoin and Ethereum.
We do have also altcoins.
What type of altcoins?
So, for example, for options, for altcoins right now, you have Solana, you have Dogecoin,
you have XRP, Litecoin, Matic, Link, Tron, Bitcoin Cash, Filecoin, and Cash.
So, I think it's...
Yeah, that's a lot.
Yeah.
To be options, it's a lot.
A lot of cryptos.
So, if you want to trade something else than Bitcoin and Ethereum on options,
CoinCall is your exchange.
When you say a tutor, are we talking about a real person?
Yes.
Or not AI?
No, no, no.
No, you can see them live.
They show their face.
Should we look at options as a speculation tool or a hedge?
Before, knowing about options, I thought it was more about speculation.
But now that I learned about options, I think it's more commonly used as a hedge by traders.
Of course, everything is a speculation when we talk about crypto.
But, I mean, compared to futures, it's much less.
So, can you tell us the advantages of options?
The first one is the limited risk and unlimited profits.
You have also portfolio coverage.
Options also allow you to benefit from a stable market price.
What's the disadvantages?
So, probably options require a little bit more of knowledge because you have more things
to review before opening positions, let's say.
Right.
Again, if you know already about futures options, it's very easy.
When you open a futures position, you don't pay a premium.
You pay maybe the fees, but that's it.
When you trade options, you pay a premium for the right to buy or sell this asset in the future.
So, coin call is a new exchange that was launched this year, 2023.
It was launched at the end of June.
It's a very young company with good professionals because we have former employees from Binance,
from FTX, from BitGet, from Deribit, from OKEx.
Also, people from JP Morgan, from Citadel.
So, it's not only a crypto, but also corporate.
We have also former KuCoin employees.
A bit of everything.
I think the most professional people from other platforms came together to build what is CoinCall today.
The vision of CoinCall is, again, that options trading will be huge in the future.
So, we want to be in the best position, in the right position when this happens for the next bull run.
We also offer futures.
And recently, we added spot trading.
Our main focus is options trading, and this is why we decided to offer options for altcoins.
That's something that other platforms don't do.
The custody of users' funds, that we don't have the custody of users' funds.
And there's a third company, which has insurance over the funds, that custodies the users' funds.
Do you see other exchanges doing the same thing, or is this a very special thing you guys are doing?
I think that in the future, when they realize that this will be the new trend,
they will jump into it.
Yes.
Big exchanges are already offering, a few of them, options for Bitcoin and Ethereum.
But I don't think they are paying a lot of attention or the attention that it really requires.
Who are you targeting?
Are you targeting experienced users or newbies?
We are targeting both.
And this is why we have launched the altcoin options trading.
And this is why we have tutors.
So we have the tutors for the newbies.
Newbies meaning users who never traded any derivative product,
but also users that are already trading futures, right, for both.
For this part, we have the tutors.
We have a very dedicated academy team.
And for the professional traders or the ones that are already trading options,
we try to provide as many tools as possible for them.
Also, discount in trading fees.
Can you summarize 2023 in one word, the crypto market?
I don't want to say regulation because I think that next year will be regulation.
So this year would be something like preparation for the regulation.
Oh, I like that.
Like doing your homework for the next year.
Yeah.
I feel like everyone who's still in crypto after this long bear market is preparing for something big.
So I like that word.
But I think that next year in the main markets,
we are going to start to see like the requirements of licenses for every exchange to be compliant,
to basically be regulated.
Maybe not the beginning of the year, but at the end of the year.
So I would say that 2023 was the preparation for 2024,
because it also includes the preparation for a potential bull run, halving of the Bitcoin.
Everything is going to happen next year.
I'm very hyped, to be honest.
So you think the bull run hasn't started yet?
I don't think so.
Really?
No, I don't think so.
Based on my previous experience in other cycles,
I think that everything happens after,
like the big jump happens after the Bitcoin halving.
Is there any indicators that indicates the train is starting?
What are some indicators that we might be able to see?
Capitalization of Bitcoin.
I think that's something that a lot of people use to see if the altcoin season is starting or not,
or when it's going to happen.
Like the percentage of the market capitalization of Bitcoin versus the other altcoins.
Can you elaborate more on that?
Yes.
When the percentage of the market capitalization of Bitcoin is really high,
and the altcoins is low,
it's probably a good moment to jump into altcoins,
because not undervaluated,
but it's a good moment to buy altcoins, let's say.
Okay.
When the percentage of the market capitalization of altcoins is increasing a lot,
and Bitcoin is going down,
then it's probably the right moment to sell,
or you are reaching the end of the altcoin season.
So it's not that very specific,
but you could see maybe a market trend.
So it's not too late to enter the market now.
It's never too late.
I like to educate everyone.
Maybe sometimes I'm even annoying,
because I only speak about cryptocurrencies.
When I talk to people,
that's a very common question.
But they tell me,
now it's too late.
It's very expensive.
They have been saying this to me for the last six, seven years.
I think it's never late.
What is your personal investing style?
Do you hold or big cap, small cap?
How do you arrange or allocate your assets?
Right now, I'm into Bitcoin and Ethereum only,
and USDT, but I don't count it.
Most of the time,
you lose more money holding other altcoins or shitcoins,
or trying to follow the trends.
In the past, I was more like a trader, gambler, let's say.
Now I would say I'm more like a holder,
but I keep trading sometimes,
and waiting patiently for the next cycle.
That is very interesting,
because hearing from someone who's been in the market for this long,
a lot of people are planning different strategies
for the next bull market.
They want to put 5% in each shitcoin,
and hopefully one of them will shoot up.
So you don't think this is a good strategy,
personally, for yourself?
Well, this is a bet, actually.
So a bet could go wrong most of the times,
but could go really well, right?
If you are lucky,
then you are going to make a lot of money more
than if you just buy Bitcoin or Ethereum.
But most of the time,
these shitcoins don't go anywhere.
So it's just a bet.
Do you look at new narratives,
and like, for example,
what's crazy in Asia right now,
the BRC20, ARC, SRC20,
like all that new thing coming out.
Do you pay attention to those things?
Yes, if I have time.
Because it depends on the time that you have,
you could dedicate this time
to learn more about the new trends.
For example, one of the new ones
that is very interesting to me
are the real world assets.
Like, for example, tokenized real estate.
And I think that this is something
that will be huge in the future
because it's very easy
for the mainstream investor to understand this.
I didn't mean that I'm not open
to all these other things.
For example, something that I like to do
is to farm airdrops.
Coincall is doing actually an airdrop next year.
Right now you can farm the Coincall token
that is going to launch in Q1 2024.
Not a specific date yet.
Everyone has the possibility right now
to farm this token in our platform.
You accumulate credits
and you can change this in the future
for Coincall token.
And it's free.
But if you want to earn more credits or faster,
then you can trade
and you can do deposits
and you earn more credits.
So if you want to farm a new token
that is for sure going to launch,
Coincall is your option.
Are you heavily invested in crypto right now
or do you have a lot of USDT waiting
to get into the market?
I'm heavily invested.
Probably 90 to 95% of my investment
is in crypto right now.
Wow.
Yes.
You're all in it.
I think that's too much,
but this is my personal bet for the next year.
Okay.
It's good to just hear people's personal opinion.
Of course, it's not financial advice,
but I'm sure you're in the market
longer than most people
or definitely a lot longer than I am in the market.
So it's good to hear your perspective.
Are we going to see old coins going to new highs
or are we going to see a bunch of new coins shooting up?
Both things, I think.
The strong ones will reach new old-time highs.
It happened before already.
And we will see the,
let's say the surge of new coins
that are not now in the top 20, top 25.
And that's very easy to see
if you go to, for example, coin market cap,
you can see historical market caps.
You can check 2019, for example.
You will see that the top 20
is very different to what we have today.
And it will happen the same in the next year or two.
So the strong ones will remain.
We'll reach new old-time highs
and we will see new opportunities, of course.
People will make money with new coins
that are not created yet.
How do you foresee the crypto market in 2024?
If you can describe it,
what do you think it's going to look like?
So I think that 2024 will be really hype.
Everyone is expecting the next year
to happen a lot of exciting things.
Not only the potential ETF
and the, for sure, Bitcoin halving.
We are reaching the end of this bear market
and we see the light at the end of the tunnel.
But we just don't know when.
When it's going to happen.
But I think that 2024 will be exciting
for many reasons.
You've seen a lot of bull and bear markets.
The next bull market,
there is a new thing called Bitcoin Spot ETF.
What's your take on the potential approval
on this ETF?
I think 2024 will be the year.
It's already priced in.
The people know about it.
Most important will be the,
what happens months after,
not right after,
the Bitcoin halving.
So you don't think this ETF will be
a buy the news type event?
It might be a sell the news type event.
Probably it will cause a short-term bump
because of the news.
But I think that everyone knows
that it's going to be approved.
They just don't know when,
but everyone knows that it's going to happen.
It's already priced in that,
again, we are going to see
probably a small bump on the price
when it happens,
when they announce it.
And it's very important
when it happens,
because if it happens
right before the Bitcoin halving
or after,
things could be different.
So it also depends on
when it's going to happen.
But that is going to happen.
I'm 100% sure.
What I'm hearing right now,
you don't think it's going to be
like a life-changing
type of wealth creation.
It could make people money,
but it's not like
the last bull market,
which was like 20X
or like 1,000X.
I don't think so.
If it happens,
I'm welcome.
Yeah, of course.
Fantastic.
I'm not saying that I don't want it.
I really want it.
But in my opinion,
I don't think that it will
cause a big bump.
Is it risky
when the whole market
is anticipating
the same event
and everyone thinks
it's going to happen?
It makes me a little
concerned and worried.
I'm like,
hey,
everyone thinks
it's going to happen.
Does that mean
it's...
I don't know.
The big players,
they already know
what to do.
You know that everyone knows
that something big
is going to happen,
but no one
is going to be the first.
You will see
like a market bump
and then
you will know
at that moment
that it's starting.
But you or me,
we are not going to know
when it's going to happen.
I'm talking about
the general
market trend,
okay?
General vision.
You don't have to anticipate this,
but you have to
jump
when it's started.
You can get into a train
when it's stopped,
right?
And wait
for this to happen,
but you are going to be
waiting there.
You don't know
how long, right?
Right.
But if you jump
while the train
is already starting
to run,
you are for sure
going somewhere.
Is there anything else
you would like to share
with the audience?
Any last thoughts?
Take your time
always to
learn about crypto
when you decide
to invest,
to try new products,
futures options,
whatever products
you want to use.
Be patient
because
if you FOMO,
that's not good
and everything
is free
on the internet.
So go there,
learn,
dedicate
the hours
that you need,
take your time
and when you are ready,
jump into crypto.
It's great
talking to you.
I always
learn so much
when I talk
to people
who's been
in the market
for a long time.
It's very refreshing
talking to you
and thank you
for being here.
Thank you very much
for inviting me.
It was fun.
Yeah,
let's hope
we can repeat
this in the future.